<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.1">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.1">
  <!ENTITY date "May 2005">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>PowerGuru</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Power Guru">
  <!ENTITY version "2.0">
  <!ENTITY xantrexdoc SYSTEM "xantrex.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY outbackdoc SYSTEM "outback.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY man SYSTEM "man.xml"> 
 ]
>

 <!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
 <article id="index" lang="en">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->
   <articleinfo>
     <title>&app; Manual V&manrevision;</title>
     <copyright>
       <year>2005</year>
       <holder>Rob Savoye</holder>
     </copyright>
<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2005</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

   -->
<!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is 
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the 
     document.  -->
    <publisher> 
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername> 
    </publisher> 

<!-- 
      Copyright (c)  2005, Free Software Foundation, Inc.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
      Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".
-->

   &legal;
   <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and 
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
	any of this. -->

    <authorgroup> 
      <author> 
	<firstname>Rob</firstname> 
	<surname>Savoye</surname> 
	<affiliation> 
	  <address> <email>rob@senecass.com</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author> 
<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
      maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
       <othercredit role="translator">
	<firstname>Latin</firstname> 
	<surname>Translator 1</surname> 
	<affiliation> 
	  <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname> 
	  <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address> 
	</affiliation>
	<contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
      </othercredit>
-->
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>&appname; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">Rob Savoye
	    <email>rob@senecass.com</email>
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 

    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;.
    </releaseinfo>
   </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index"> 
    <primary>PowerGuru</primary> 
  </indexterm>

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="intro"> <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This is power monitoring system for Xantrex (was Trace)
     and Outback Power Systems products.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="betterintro">
      <title>What is &appname; ?</title>
      <para>&appname; is a tool for remotely controlling Xantrex and
      Outback Power Systems products. In my case, an old Trace 4024 and
      an Outback MX-60.
      </para>

      <para>This all started when I bought a fixer upper, off-grid
	house... Like many projects, this one seems to have fallen
	into my lap, more than it was a concious idea. Over time, the
	concept has evolved into an actual product in
	development. That project, <ulink type="http"
	url="http://www.senecass.com/abelmon">AbelMon</ulink>, is a
	much larger project, and this application
	<application>&appname;</application>, is part of that project
	spun off into a standalone application.</para>

      <para>There are other similar products, but for WinDoze are
        <ulink type="http" url="http://www.righthandeng.com">Right
        Hand Engineer's Winverter</ulink> or <ulink type="http"
        url="http://www.mauisolarsoftware.com"> Maui Solar Software's
        TraceTools</ulink>.</para>

    </sect2>    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="PowerGuru Overview">
    <title>PowerGuru Overview</title>

    <para>
      PowerGuru is an interface to your Inverter or charge
      controller. It's main purpose is to handle the low-level
      work of reading and writing from these devices. At this level
      PowerGuru is an SDK for C,C++, or Java programers to work with
      Xantrex and Outback products.
    </para>

    <para>
      The backend of PowerGuru is a daemon that runs all the time and
      is connected via serial ports to your power production
      equipment. This daemon handles all the ugly work of interfacing
      with each device. The daemon has two modes, one is data-logging
      mode, and the other is a command mode.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="Project Goals">
      <title>Project Goals</title>

      <para>
	The goals of this are project are to make it easy to datalog or
	remotely control your inverter or charge controller. The
	daemon is designed to be reasonably small, so it can run on
	12VDC low-power computer systems 24 hours a day, 7 days a
	week. Since everything is done through a network interface, a
	GUI can use the SDK to talk to the backend for all
	functionality. This makes it easier for somebody (not me, I
	suck at GUIs) to write good GUIs, without having to reverse
	engineer these protocols like I have. I'd prefer to stick to
	bit-twiddling.
      </para>

      <para>
	If I'm not home, like on a business trip, I want to be able to
	check on the status of my house while I'm gone. I have had
	weird things happen like needing to reboot the charge
	controller, or a few fuses in the combiner box blowing for no
	apparent reason. I'd also like to be able to store the default
	configuration settings for my inverter or controller, and set
	a new one with my prefered default settings off disk after a
	full system reset.
      </para>

      <para>
	If a house is a rental and you are the landlord, or you have
	an off-grid vacation house, or you are a solar installer, and
	want to offer remote support for your customers as an
	additional service, this is the type of thing I want PowerGuru
	to support.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Data Logging Mode">
      <title>PowerGuru Data Logging Mode</title>
      
      <para>
	In this mode, the PowerGuru daemon just polls all the devices
	that have output data, and writes it directly to an SQL
	database. The time between data collection cycles can be set
	by the user, since the amount of data can be huge, and doesn't
	often vary much.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="Command Mode">
      <title>PowerGuru Command Mode</title>
      
      <para>
	In this mode, the PowerGuru daemon acts as the remote agent to
	control the device. Client programs use a network connection
	(I'm contemplating using SNMP) to operate the commands
	supported by each device. This enables the settings of each
	device to be stored and set remotely.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="User Interfaces">
      <title>User Interfaces</title>

      <para>
	There are two planned user interfaces for PowerGuru. One is web
	based, and will enable the plotting of the logged data in
	various forms. The other interface is designed to run standalone
	without the need for a PHP enabled web server. It is also
	designed to be run from a PDA or laptop in the field with a
	direct serial connection to the device. This is for installers
	so they can download the default settings they prefer to the
	device, or extract the current device settings to store in a
	disk file.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="Web Interface">
	<title>Web Interface</title>

	<para>
	  The web interface is written in PHP, and should be supported
	  by most all web servers and browsers. This is primarily a
	  data mining and display application to plot the power
	  readings in graphical manner. This UI is currently under
	  development.
	</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="Standalone Interface">
	<title>Standalone Interface</title>

	<para>
	  I want to be able to run PowerGuru on multiple systems,
	  namely Linux, Darwin, and Win32. The choice of a
	  cross-platform user interface toolkit that runs on all three
	  is not a trivial decision. Most PDAs these days runs Qtopia
	  (written in QT), PalmOS, or WinCE. Other than Java, a
	  language I truly dislike, the only multi-platform
	  solution supported on all platforms is QT. (called Qtopia on
	  a PDA) I'm not a GUI programer, I'm an embedded systems
	  type, so I'd prefer to only write the GUI once.
	</para>

	<para>
	  I have long prefered GTK+/GNOME over QT/KDE mostly cause I'm
	  a "free software" purist, and I'm not sure I want to learn
	  either QT or Java right now anyway. The original GUI for
	  PowerGuru back when it was still called "TraceGUI" was
	  written in GTK1.2, using the Glade prototyper. This can run
	  on Linux, Darwin and Win32, but not my PDA.
	</para>

	<para>
	  It is possible to run Tcl/Tk on most PDAs as an addon
	  package. For my Zaurus it needs an X11 environment (I run
	  OpenZaurus (a Debian port) on my Zaurus), plus Gentoo also
	  runs on the Zaurus with X11 support. There are also native
	  Tcl/Tk ports for PalmOS and WinCE, and it has a visual
	  development environment as well. I also used to be one of
	  the Tcl/Tk maintainers, so I wouldn't have the learning
	  curve and time drain of using QT or Java.
	</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="Protocol Reference">
    <title>Protocol Reference</title>

    <para>
      PowerGuru supports multiple protocols, since it supports
      multiple devices. As documentation of these protocols is often
      non-existant or there is a lot of supporting info needed by
      developers that isn't covered in the existing manuals, I figured
      I'd document my experiences with these systems from my
      perspective as an embedded systems engineer with over 25 years
      experience.
    </para>

    &xantrexdoc;

    &outbackdoc;

  </sect1>

<!-- ============= Authors ================================ -->

  <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Authors</title>
    <para>
      <application>PowerGuru</application> was written by Rob Savoye
      (<email>rob@senecass.com</email>).  Please send all comments,
      suggestions, and bug reports to <email>rob@senecass.com</email>. 
      I am available for consulting on a variety of renewable energy
      and open source technologies. More details at <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.senecass.com">http://www.senecass.com</ulink>
   </para>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ============= Application License ============================= -->

  <sect1 id="license">
   <title>License</title>
   <para>
    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the <citetitle>GNU General Public
    License</citetitle> as published by the Free Software Foundation;
    either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
    version.
   </para>
   <para>
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
    WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> for more details.
   </para>
   <para>
    A copy of the <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> is
    included as an appendix to the <citetitle>GNOME Users
    Guide</citetitle>.  You may also obtain a copy of the
    <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> from the Free
    Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http"
    url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to
    <address>
     Free Software Foundation, Inc.
     <street>51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor</street>
     <city>Boston</city>, <state>MA</state> <postcode>02111-1301</postcode>
     <country>USA</country>
    </address>
   </para>
  </sect1>
</article>




